Florian Vichot

devOps engineer

Sydney, Australia +61 402 936 579 Florian.vichot@gmail.com florian

An accomplished software engineer, I have more than ten years of experience, comprising both development and operations. Fluent in multiple programming languages and technologies, I strive foremost to be versatile, and to be able to efficiently solve a broad range of problems. While drawn primarily to the roles of SRE, devOps, infrastructure or backend engineer, I welcome all opportunities that would allow me to work on challenging and varied problems as part of a talented team. Projects with an open-source model or tackling social issues are especially attractive.

EXPERIENCE

Infrastructure & Network Engineer — Wifirst — Paris, France — April 2016 to May 2018

- > Developing new functionalities and tools in Python for a custom network router, to provide traffic shaping, access control and monitoring for our customers.
- > Supervision of a fleet of over 12,000 CPE routers, managed through Ansible.
- > Designing and evolving our monitoring infrastructure to handle a large volume of requests per second.
- > Testing and selecting new hardware for the router.
- > Porting the services and OS used on our custom router to a new architecture based on a Broadcom SoC.
- > Speaker at PyCon France 2017

Python Django Nginx Bash Git Ansible iptables SNMP QoS VLAN WiFi Network DevOps

Senior Software Engineer — Inria, Asclepios Lab — Sophia-Antipolis, France — March 2012 to April 2015

- > Lead developer on medlnria, an open-source medical image visualisation, processing and manipulation software, to add cardiac related functionalities.
- > Contributed to improving the reliability of medInria, and its code quality by instituting code-reviews and a pull-request based workflow. Migrated the project to GitHub, reorganised, cleaned and simplified the source code, re-architected and updated the build/test system.
- > Evolved medInria's architecture to handle new functionalities, and transformed it into a framework for other projects using a plugin system.
- > Attended conferences (MICCAI), workshops (CTK), and contributed to scientific articles.

C++ Python Bash Git CMake Jenkins Open-Source Qt VTK ITK Mac Windows Linux

Systems & Network Engineer — Telecoms Without Borders — Pau, France — Sept. 2010 to Oct. 2011, April 2015

- > Deployed on various international missions in response to humanitarian emergencies: floods, influx of refugees, cyclone, conflict or famine, for a total of 5 months on mission. Established telephone operations for populations, installed network and satellite equipment for NGOs and the UN. Provided trainings.
- > Maintained and evolved the NGO's infrastructure (website, email servers, storage, equipment database)
- > Contributed to the TSFBox, a network router facilitating monitoring and optimization of internet connections provided during missions.

Perl Python Bash iptables System administration Networks Satellites Linux

Developer — Diateam — Brest, France — June 2008 to April 2010, July/August 2007

- > Lead developer on the Hynesim (Hybrid Network Simulator) and contributor to the IpMorph (TCP/IP stack fingerprint spoofing) open-source projects. Speaker on IpMorph during Hack.lu 2009.
- > Developer on Diabox, an in-situ sensor box and web service, used primarily for weather data.
- > Developer on Naiad (Enhanced Satellite Archive Dataminer), an web application to visualise and process satellite data for the IFREMER institute. Prototyped various image filters on GPU using OpenCL.

C C++ PHP Python Open-Source Qt Multi-Thread Container Virtualisation OpenCL Mac Windows Linux

Internship — Cognitive Robotics Lab (ENSTA) — Paris, France — Sept. 2007 to Jan. 2008

- > Implemented visual homing and localization algorithms using "bags of visual words" in Urbi, as part of a topological navigation framework.
- > Ported the Urbi environment to a P3-DX robot.
- > This work was included in a scientific publication.
- C C++ Urbi SVN Machine-Learning Linux Robotics

PERSONAL PROJECTS

Robotics Club — ENIB — Brest, France — 2004 to 2010

- > Club secretary: sponsors engagement, communication, project management.
- > Lead developer on the robot's software (simulator, sensor acquisition, path planning, motor control)

C C++ Qt OpenGL SVN Linux Embedded Robotics Algorithms

Server management -2011 to 2015

> Server administrator for a club: configuration, security, supervision.

Linux Debian iptables Apache PHP OwnCloud Zimbra OpenVPN IMAP SMTP LVM LUKS KVM LXC RAID

SKILLS

Languages Excellent	Tools and concepts Excellent	Networks & Servers Excellent	Platforms Excellent
C C++ Python2/3 Bash	Qt Git Django CMake Multi-threading CI/CD	Internet protocols Sysadmin Server security	Linux (Debian/Fedora) Mac OS X Windows 7/8/10
Good	Good	Good	Good
Go JavaScript Java Octave	OpenGL OpenCL SQL Algorithms Optimisation	SSL OpenVPN IPSec AWS Satellite systems	Cisco IOS ZynOS Digi
Basic			Basic
Rust Haskell			OpenBSD JunOS

LANGUAGES

- > French: Fluent (French citizen)
- > English: Fluent (studied for three years in the UK, TOEFL iBT: 119/120, PTE: 90/90)
- > Spanish: Intermediate (six months in South America)

EDUCATION

- > ENIB, National Engineering School of Brest, France from 2003 to 2008 (Master's Degree in Engineering).
- > Artificial Intelligence online course, University of Stanford, 2012.
- > Machine Learning online course, Stanford University, 2015 (Coursera).

PUBLICATIONS

Cardiac Interventional Guidance using Multimodal Data Processing and Visualisation: medlnria as an Interoperability Platform — Midas Journal — 2012

Authors: F. Vichot, H. Cochet, B. Bleuzé, N. Toussaint, P. Jaïs, M. Sermesant

Summary: MedInria is a medical imaging software developed at Inria, which aims to provide clinicians with state-of-theart algorithms for processing and visualising their images. In this article, we will focus on its use in pre-surgery preparation for cardiac interventions, and the difficulties arising from the lack of standardisation of certain data formats and visualisation conventions.

IpMorph: fingerprinting spoofing unification — Journal in computer virology 6, no. 4-2010

Authors: G. Prigent, F. Vichot, F. Harrouet

Summary: Nowadays, there are a variety of tools for easily identifying the TCP/IP stack's fingerprint of a target machine. IpMorph allows this fingerprint to be concealed, and even mimicks the fingerprint of a chosen TCP/IP stack. This is done through live session tracking and packet rewriting. Its effectiveness against tools such as Nmap, Xprobe2, Ring2, SinFP and p0f is also detailed.